Preliminary inventory of the Karl R. Bendetsen papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Karl R. Bendetsen papers
1917-1989
75100
Hoover Institution Archives
716 manuscript boxes, 8 oversize boxes, 2 album boxes, 2 motion picture film reels, 6 sound cassettes, 1 videotape cassette, 1 framed certificate (313.2 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, speeches, studies, interview transcripts, minutes, statements, orders, printed matter, scrapbooks, and audiovisual materials relating to the internment of Japanese Americans during World War II, American military organization and military policy during World War II and the Korean War, subsequent American defense policy, the Strategic Defense Initiative, American foreign policy, and the Champion International Corporation. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Bendetsen, Karl R.
Access
Collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Use copies of some sound recordings in this collection are available for immediate access. To listen to other sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical Note
American business executive; assistant and under secretary of the Army, 1950-1952; special United States representative to West Germany, 1956; special ambassador to the Philippines, 1956; chairman, Advisory Committee to the Secretary of Defense, 1962; president and chairman of the board, Champion International Corporation, 1952-1973.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, speeches, studies, interview transcripts, minutes, statements, orders, printed matter, scrapbooks, and audiovisual materials relating to the internment of Japanese Americans during World War II, American military organization and military policy during World War II and the Korean War, subsequent American defense policy, the Strategic Defense Initiative, American foreign policy, and the Champion International Corporation.
Champion International Corporation.; United States. Army.; United States. Department of Defense.; Audiotapes.; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.; Korean War, 1950-1953.; Motion pictures.; Strategic Defense Initiative.; United States--Defenses.; United States--Military policy.; Video tapes.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.
- U.S. Army, 1940-1946
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains army officer papers, including material relating to relocation of Japanese Americans and declassified records returned to the collection in May and September of 2011.
  - Army officer papers, 1940-1946 (Boxes 391, 554-559, 565-566, 608-612, 621, 627, 632, 643, 683-684, 717-720)
  - 2011 release of declassified government records, 1920-1943 (Reading room Workstation)
    The May 2011 declassified records release consists of the plan for Operation Rankin, August 1943 (originals in box 684). The September 2011 declassified records release consists of the plan for Operation Overlord, 30 July 1943.
- Oral history interview, 1972 (Box 486)
  Relates to Japanese American relocation.
- Retrospective materials, 1980s (Boxes 613-614, 620, 628-631)
  Relates to Japanese American relocation and reparations proposals. Includes hearing transcripts.
- Management counsel, 1946-1948 (Box 595)
- U.S. Department of Defense, 1948-1952 (Boxes 685, 693-700, 703-705, 721, 722)
  Includes papers as assistant and under secretary of the Army. Box 721 contains oversize material and box 722 contains photographs.
- Panama Canal Company, 1952-1954 (Boxes 656-662, 668)
  Contains papers from when Bendetsen served as member of the Board of Directors.
- Champion International Corporation, 1952-1989 (Boxes 1-379, 392-452, 498-500, 540-541, 560-561, 578-580, 585-586, 590-594, 597, 626, 665-667, 686-690, 706-714, 723)
  Contains papers from when Bendetsen served as executive of the corporation and its predecessors, Champion Papers Company and U.S. Plywood-Champion Papers Corporation, until 1973, and subsequently as member of its Board of Directors. Boxes 686-690 contain speeches and box 723 contains oversize material.
- Philippines Mission, 1956 (Boxes 669, 675)
  Contains papers from when Bendetsen served as a special U.S. representative to negotiate a military base agreement.
- Advisory Committee to the Secretary of Defense on Non-Military Instruction, 1962 (Boxes 380-389)
  Contains papers from when Bendetsen served as chairman of the committee.
- Conference on National Security: The Demands of Strategy and Economics in the Decade Ahead, Center for Strategic Studies, Georgetown University, 1963 (Box 390)
- Industrial College of the Armed Forces, 1965-1972 (Boxes 596, 602)
  Contains papers from when Bendetsen served as a member of the Board of Advisers.
- New York Stock Exchange, 1973-1981 (Boxes 453-468, 470, 473, 476-480, 512-514, 519, 521-524, 526-531, 537-539, 567-569, 573-577, 581-584, 603-607, 636-640, 644, 650-652, 670-674, 701)
  Contains papers from when Bendetsen served as a member of the Board of Directors.
- Defense Manpower Commission, 1974-1976 (Boxes 481-485, 487-489, 503-507, 691-692)
  Papers from Bendetsen's time as vice chairman of the commission.
- Diebold Venture Capital Corporation, 1975-1977 (Boxes 471-472, 702)
- Westinghouse Electric Corporation, 1976-1979 (Boxes 469, 474-475, 548, 562-564, 570, 598-601, 623-625, 715)
  Contains papers from Bendetsen time as a member of the Board of Directors.
- High Frontier Panel and Strategic Defense Initiative Advisory Committee, 1981-1985 (Boxes 676-682)
  Contains papers from when Bendetsen served as a member of the panel and committee.
- Retirement papers, 1973-1989 (Boxes 490-497, 501-502, 508-511, 515-518, 520, 525, 532-536, 542-547, 549-553, 571-572, 587-589, 615-619, 622, 633-635, 641-642, 645-649, 653-655, 663-664, 716, 724)
  Box 724 contains oversize material.
- Sound recordings, undated
  - Champion International Corporation - Telephone conversation about land use (Reading room Workstation)
    Access
    Use copy reference number: 75100_a_0010257
    Unlabeled Audograph Soundwriter disc which has been bent radially due to a paper clip holding it for an extended period of time. Original in box 16.
  - Karl R. Bendetsen interview about the Japanese-American interment camps, 2 sound cassettes (Reading room Workstation)
    Use copy reference number: 75100_a_0010376
    Interviewer: Ken Ringle of the Washington Post. Originals in cassette cabinet.
  - Karl R. Bendetsen Boca Raton interview, 4 sound cassettes (Reading room Workstation)
    Use copy reference number: 75100_a_0010377
    Originals in cassette cabinet.